<sapia:page title="Installation" xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <head>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/corus.css" type="text/css"/>
  </head>

  <sapia:sect1 title="Installation">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus" href="home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="installation" />
    </sapia:section>
    
    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <p>Corus is designed with simplicity in mind: to come up with a simple solution to a complex (and non-trivial)
      problematic. The installation of Corus is no exception. We provide distributions for different operating
      systems to suits your needs. Regardless of the OS you are using, we take care to provided a seemless integration
      to optimize the various functionnalities offered by each platform.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect-desc>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Supported Operating Systems">
      <p>Technically speaking, Corus should run on any platform that supports Java. However, manually starting java
      programs using custom scripts is kind of cumbersome. That is why we provide specialized scripts for each OS to
      manage the Corus runtime. We also provide an integration with operating services to automatically start Corus
      on startup (when available by the OS) and to monitor the Corus process in case of abnormal process termination.
      </p>
      <p>Here's the list of what we support at the moment:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Windows">
        <p><ul>
        <li>Ability to register Corus as a Windows service to run at startup and to manage execution lifecycle (stop, start, restart)</li>
        <li>Various .bat files to manually execute the corus server runtime and other tools provided (CLI, monitor, ...)</li>
        <li>Only 32 bits version is available for native intergation</li>
        <li>Tested on Windows XP and Windows Vista. Windows 7 yet to come...</li>
        </ul></p>
      </sapia:sect3>
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Mac OS">
        <p><ul>
        <li>Integration with Mac <tt>launchd</tt> manager to run Corus as a LaunchDaemon or a LaunchAgent (based on your specific needs)</li>
        <li>Various shell scripts to manually execute the corus server runtime and other tools provided (CLI, monitor, ...)</li>
        <li>32 bits version available for OS X 10.5 (leopard) and above</li>
        <li>64 bits version available for OS X 10.6 (snow leopard)</li>
        <li>Tested on both Leopard (OS X 10.5) and Snow Leopard (OS X 10.6)</li>
        </ul></p>
      </sapia:sect3>
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Linux">
        <p><ul>
        <li>init.d like script to integrate Corus to the Linux run levels (using special features like chkconfig when available)</li>
        <li>Various shell scripts to manually execute the corus server runtime and other tools provided (CLI, monitor, ...)</li>
        <li>32 bits and 64 bits versions available</li>
        <li>Tested on many flavours of Linux: CentOS, Ubuntu, Fedora, Mandriva, OpenSUSE</li>
        </ul></p>
      </sapia:sect3>
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Solaris">
        <p><ul>
        <li>Integration with the Service Management Facility (SMF) to manage Corus as a system service within Solaris</li>
        <li>Various shell scripts to manually execute the corus server runtime and other tools provided (CLI, monitor, ...)</li>
        <li>Support for both Sparc (32 and 64 bits) and x86 platform (32 bits only)</li>
        <li>Tested with openSolaris 2009.06 on a x86 platform</li>
        </ul></p>
      </sapia:sect3>

      <p><b>Your operating system is not in that list?</b><br/>
      Contact us [TODO: insert email|ggroup link] so we can support you in the integration of your platform.
      Your contribution will benefit to the whole community.
      </p>
       
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Download">
      <p>The various Corus distributions can be found here [TODO: insert link to gcode download page]. Make sure to select
      the appropriate version based on your operating system and your hardware architecture.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Setup">
      <p>Because the configuration differs from one operating system to another, we will only  provide an overview of the setup
      process. We provide an installation section in our wiki [TODO: insert link] where step-by-step instructions are given
      to install an configure Corus on the system of your choice.  
      </p>

      <p><b>1. Preparing the environment</b><br/>
      Define pre-requisites like user and groups, directory structure, ...
      </p>      

      <p><b>2. Extract the corus distribution</b><br/>
      ...
      </p>      

      <p><b>3. Define environment variables</b><br/>
      Define JAVA_HOME and CORUS_HOME environment variables....
      </p>      

      <p><b>4. OS integration</b><br/>
      Registration/integration with OS specifiy facility to automatically manage Corus runtime lifecycle....
      </p>      
      
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Test">
      <p>You want to see Corus in action? Like the people in the midwest you are saying: "Show me!!!". We provide sample
      applications ready to be deployed in the server. You can look for the files in the /samples directory [TODO: validate directory name] of the distribution or
      you can jump to the tutorial section [TODO: insert link to tutorial] were you will find more explanation on what the samples are and how to
      deploy them.   
      </p>
      <p>In any case, have fun and enjoy!
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
