<sapia:page title="core:parameters" xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform" cssPath="../../css/sapia.css">
  <sapia:sect1 title="core:parameters">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="magnet" href="../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="manual" href="../home.html#Core%20Elements" />
      <sapia:path name="core:parameters" />
    </sapia:section>
    <toc />
        
    <sapia:sect2 title="Overview">
	    <p>The <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command> element defines a group
	    of variables in a magnet configuration file. By itself this element does not define
	    any variable but rather contains a list of <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command>
	    elements. The main functionnality of this element is to associate all the variables
	    it contains to a given profile; so this element is <b>profile-aware</b>.
	    </p>
	
	    <p>
	    Using the profile attribute we can perform such associations. This attribute is optional
	    and the presence (or abscence) of this attribute has the following meaning: if the profile is not
	    provided, then all the variables it contains are considered "global" and they
	    are always rendered and available. If the profile attribute is defined then the 
	    variables it contains will only be rendered and be available when a magnet is executed 
	    for that specific profile.
	    </p>
    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Attributes">
      <p>The following list the xml attributes of the <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command> element:
      </p>
	  <sapia:table>
	    <sapia:th>Name</sapia:th>
	    <sapia:th>Description</sapia:th>
	    <sapia:th>Required</sapia:th>
	    <sapia:th>Interpolation</sapia:th>
	    <tr>
	      <td>profile</td>
	      <td>The name of the profile to which this group of parameters will be associated.</td>
	      <td>no</td>
	      <td>no</td>
	    </tr>
	  </sapia:table>
    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Child Elements">
      <p>The following lists the possible child xml elements that can hold the <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command> element:
      </p>
      <sapia:table>
        <sapia:th>Name</sapia:th>
        <sapia:th>Cardinality</sapia:th>
        <sapia:th>Description</sapia:th>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="#Param" target="main">param</a></td>
          <td>0 or *</td>
          <td>Each param child element defines a given variable.</td>
        </tr>
      </sapia:table>
    </sapia:sect2>


    <sapia:sect2 title="Rendering Operations">
		  <p>When a <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command> element is rendered, it performs the following
		  operations in order:
		    <ol>
		      <li>Renders each param definition it contains. A param will be rendered only if the evaluation of
            the conditionnal attributes "if" <b>and</b> "unless" is true; otherwise the param
            is skipped and the rendering process goes on to the next param.</li>
		      <li>Adds each param to the magnet context or to the system properties (depending on the scope).</li>
		    </ol>
		  </p>
    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Examples">
		  <p>This first example defines a parameters element that would contains global variables.</p>
		  <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParametersExample1"
        description="This is a simple example.">
...
    <parameters>
        ...
    </parameters>
...
</magnet>]]></sapia:code>

		  <p>This second example defines a parameters element that would contains variables associated
		  to a "dev" profile.</p>
		  <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParametersExample2"
        description="This is a second example.">
...
    <parameters profile="dev">
        ...
    </parameters>
...
</core:magnet>]]></sapia:code>

    </sapia:sect2>

	  <sapia:sect2 title="Nested Element Definition">
      <sapia:sect3 title="Param">
        <p>The <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command> element defines a parameter or a variable
        containing a value that may be referenced in a magnet configuration file. This element is
        always nested within a <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command> element and basically consists
        of a name-value pair. Because it is alway within a <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command>
        element, the value of a variable will be assigned (or not) according to the profile of that element;
        variables of "default" parameters will always be rendeder and variables of a specific profile will
        only be rendered if that profile was specified at startup.
        </p>

        <p>If a variable is defined more than once for different <sapia:command>&lt;parameters&gt;</sapia:command>,
        the value of that variable can be overridden, meaning the value of the variable will change
        according to the profile in which the magnet is run. If a variable is defined globally
        (not associated to a profile) and the same variable is defined for a specific profile, the
        value of the variable will be the one defined for the profile if the magnet is executed for it.
        </p>

        <p>The value of a variable can contain another variable name using the notation
        <sapia:command>${variable_name}</sapia:command>. The only care to take in that situation is to
        make sure that the variable it refers to is already define. Since the variables are processed
        sequentially in magnet, you would need to define your <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command>
        element before you use the variable in the value of another.
        </p>

        <p>Each variable that is defined in a magnet configuration file can reside in virtually two
        places. The scope attribute of the <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command> element gives
        us a way to define where we want a variable to reside. Two values are possible for that attribute:
        <ul>
            <li><b>magnet</b> - The variable will be added to the magnet context and the value will
            only be accessible from within magnet.</li>
            <li><b>system</b> - The variable will be added to the java system properties and the
            value will be accessible accross the VM.</li>
        </ul>
        </p>

        <sapia:note>
          When a variable is resolved using the interpolation mechanism, magnet always looks in the
          magnet context first. If it's not present it will then look in the system properties.
        </sapia:note>

        <sapia:sect4 title="Attributes">
          <p>The following list the xml attributes of the <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command> element:
          </p>
          <sapia:table>
            <sapia:th>Name</sapia:th>
            <sapia:th>Description</sapia:th>
            <sapia:th>Required</sapia:th>
            <sapia:th>Interpolation</sapia:th>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>The name of the variable to define.</td>
              <td>yes</td>
              <td>no</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>value</td>
              <td>The value to assign to this variable.</td>
              <td>yes</td>
              <td>yes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>scope</td>
              <td><p>The scope of a variable can only be "magnet" or "system". If this attribute
              is ommitted by default the scope is "magnet".</p>
              </td>
              <td>no</td>
              <td>yes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>if</td>
              <td><p>Condition that makes this variable effective only if the value represents a
              variable name that have a value in the magnet context or in the system properties.</p>
              </td>
              <td>no</td>
              <td>yes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>unless</td>
              <td><p>Condition that makes this variable effective only if the value represents a
              variable name that does not have a value in the magnet context or in the system properties.</p>
              </td>
              <td>no</td>
              <td>yes</td>
            </tr>
          </sapia:table>
        </sapia:sect4>

        <sapia:sect4 title="Rendering Operations">
          <p>When a <sapia:command>&lt;param&gt;</sapia:command> element is rendered, it performs the following
          operations in order:
            <ol>
              <li>Resolve the value, scope , if and unless attributes (using variable interpolation).</li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </sapia:sect4>

        <sapia:sect4 title="Param Examples">
          <p>This first example defines two sets of the same variables: foo and username. The example shows
          how to use the variable value overload feature of magnet. If that magnet would be run for a "dev"
          profile, the value of the foo variable would be bar2, otherwise the value of the variable would be
          bar.</p>
          <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParamExample1"
        description="This is a simple example.">
...
    <parameters>
        <param name="foo"      value="bar" />
        <param name="username" value="scott" />
    </parameters>

    <parameters profile="dev">
        <param name="foo"      value="bar2" />
        <param name="username" value="developer" />
    </parameters>
...
</magnet>]]></sapia:code>

          <p>This second example shows how to export variables to the java system properties using
          the scope attribute. In that example the hostname variable would be added the the system
          properties. The result is the same as adding the argument <sapia:command>-Dhostname=myhost.mydomain.com</sapia:command>
          to the command line when invoking a java VM.</p>
          <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParamExample2"
        description="This is a second example.">
...
    <parameters>
        <param name="hostname" value="myhost.mydomain.com" scope="system" />
        <param name="port"     value="80" />
    </parameters>
...
</magnet>]]></sapia:code>

          <p>In this third example we see that the <sapia:command>server.url</sapia:command> variable
          incorporates other variables in its own value. When we run that magnet for the dev profile, the
          <sapia:command>server.url</sapia:command> variable would have the value
          <sapia:command>http://192.168.57.100:80</sapia:command>.
          </p>
          <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParamExample3"
        description="This is a third example.">
...
    <parameters>
        <param name="server.port" value="80" />
    </parameters>

    <parameters profile="dev">
      <param name="server.ip"  value="192.168.57.100" />
      <param name="server.url" value="http://${server.ip}:${server.port}" />
    </parameters>
...
</magnet>]]></sapia:code>

          <p>In this fourth example we are using the <sapia:command>if</sapia:command> and
            <sapia:command>unless</sapia:command> attributes to perform conditional variable
            assignment. The first variable, <sapia:command>magnet.home</sapia:command>, will
            be assigned the value of <sapia:command>user.dir</sapia:command> 
            <b>only if</b> it is was not previously assigned and a
            <sapia:command>msg</sapia:command> variable will be assigned the value
            "<sapia:command>Using the provided magnet.home</sapia:command>" if the variable
            <sapia:command>magnet.home</sapia:command> is assigned.
          </p>
          <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<magnet xmlns="http://schemas.sapia-oss.org/magnet/core/"
        name="ParamExample3"
        description="This is a third example.">
...
    <parameters>
        <param name="magnet.home" value="${user.dir}"
               unless="magnet.home" scope="system"/>
        <param name="msg" value="Using the provided magnet.home"
               if="magnet.home" scope="system"/>
    </parameters>
...
</magnet>]]></sapia:code>
        </sapia:sect4>

      </sapia:sect3>

	  </sapia:sect2>

  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>